Guide to the Wood Gray papers, 1918-1973 MS0246.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Wood Gray papers
1918-1973
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Gray, Wood
MS0246.UA
6 Linear Feet
Collection include materials related Wood Gray's time at GW as professor of History, and includes annual reports, correspondence, committee reports, reading lists, syllabi, grades, exams. They range in date from 1934-72.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Biographical Note
Wood Gray (1905-1977) was Professor of History at The George Washington University from 1934-72. He was born March 19, 1905 in Petersburg, Illinois. He graduated from Petersburg Harris High school as valedictorian. He was also the captain of the track team. He attended the University of Illinois and earned his B.A. in 1927 and M.A. in 1928. While there he was a member of Phi Beta Kappa Phi Delta Kappa, Tau Kappa Epsilon, Phi Eta Sigma. A sports enthusiast, he was a student manager for the college football team, and years later liked to tell the story of taping the ankles of Hall of Fame player Red Grange before the Michigan game in which Grange scored five touchdowns. Gray received his Ph.D. from the University of Chicago in 1933, and began his career at GW the following year. He was chairman of the department from 1937-53 and 1964-65. During World War II he served in the Army Air Corps, Special Staff, as a Lt. Colonel from 1943-46.
While at GW he was a founding member of the chapter of Phi Beta Kappa. He led the drive for one of the nation's most liberal faculty codes, concerning tenure and faculty rights, as a member of the Faculty Senate. He served as secretary to the American Association of University Professors for two terms and was the United States history section editor for the American Historical Review for more than twenty years. Dr. Gray helped integrate the Cosmos Club in Washington as a member of the admissions committee, bringing in as a member fellow historian John Hope Franklin.
Dr. Gray specialized in American social history and the Civil War. He served as a consultant for the United States Information Agency in the preparation of histories and motion pictures for overseas distribution and lectured at the Foreign Service Institute and Industrial College of the Armed Forces. He wrote "Historian's Handbook: A Key to the Study and Writing of History," (1951) a guidebook for students of history that was used in more than five-hundred colleges and universities. He was also author of "The Hidden Civil War: The Story of the Copperheads" (1942) and co-author with Marcus W. Jernigan of "Essays in American Historiography" (1937). Dr. Gray was made Professor Emeritus in 1972.
He summed up his philosophy of history thus: "Man's unique ability to incorporate into personal experience that of all other men and women, not only of his own time but all previous generations, is a true second sight that sets him above other species and enables him better to understand the present in order to prepare himself to face the problems of the future." Dr. Gray married Dorothea Leal Gray August 13, 1927. She died in 1978. Dr. Gray died on June 27, 1977 in Washington, D.C.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include photos (including World War II, family, William Collier, Cloyd Heck Marvin, Charles Swisher), journals of notes taken while a student at University of Illinois, correspondence, annual reports, committee reports, reading lists, syllabi, grades, exams, and a framed George Washington coat of arms transparency. They range in date from 1918-73, and their provenance is unclear. Two accessions were added to the University Archives in 1987 and 1995.
Collection Organization
Organized in two series, Papers and Photographs, journals.
Photographs; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Washington (D.C.); Reports and dissertations; Phi Beta Kappa; Examinations; American Association of University Professors; George Washington University; Gray, Wood
- Papers, 1934-1972; MS0246 Series 1; 2 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Materials in this collection include materials related to Gray's time at GW, annual reports, correspondence, committee reports, reading lists, syllabi, grades, exams. They range in date from 1934-72, and their provenance is unclear. The accession was added to the University Archives in 1987.
  - GWU Posts: Professor of American History, 1934-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - GWU Posts: Professor of American History, recommendations, 1935-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - GWU Posts: Chairman, Faculty Advisory Committee (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - GWU Posts: Chairman, Department of History (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - GWU Posts: Executive Officer, Department of History (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - GWU Posts: Executive Officer, Department of History (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - GWU Posts: Chairman, Faculty Advisory Committee (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - GWU Posts: Department of History, Advisory Committee (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - GWU Correspondence: Department of History, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - GWU Correspondence: Department of History, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - GWU Faculty Annual Reports, (incomplete), 1965-1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - GWU Awards: Professor Emeritus of American History, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - GWU: Advisory Committee's reports (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - GWU: Advisory Committee's reports (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - GWU: University Senate, Committee on Student relation (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - GWU: University Senate, Committee on University Objectives (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - GWU: University Senate, Committee on Scholarships (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - GWU: Committee on Graduate Admissions (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - GWU Courses: History 171 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - GWU Courses: History 171, final examinations (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - GWU Courses: History 171, Syllabi (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - GWU Courses: History 185, grades (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - GWU Courses: History 199-200, exams (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - GWU Courses: History 199-201, grades (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - GWU Courses: History 171-172, syllabi (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - GWU Courses: Reading lists, general (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - GWU Courses: Reading lists, general (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - GWU Courses: Book reports (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - GWU Alumni Association, L.A. Chapter, 1949-1962 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - GWU Alumni Association, L.A. Chapter, 1949-1962 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - GWU General Alumni Association, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - GWU Fraternity TKE Historical Commission (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - GWU Alumni Association, financial records (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - GWU Faculty Club (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - GWU Organizations, Orchesis. (dance) [1/2] (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - GWU Organizations, Orchesis. (dance) [2/2] (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - American Association of University Professors, Committee "T" (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - AAUP, Committee "T" (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - AAUP, Committee "T" (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - AAUP, Committee "T" (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - American Historical Association (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Cosmos CLub (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Industrial College of the Armed Forces Seminar (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Publications: The Hidden Civil War, Publisher's correspondence (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Invitations to Speak (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Personal correspondence (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - William McLain, letters (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Photos and postcards (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Photographs and journals, 1918-1973; MS0246 Series 2; 4 Linear feet
  Materials in this collection include photos (including World War II, family, William Collier, Cloyd Heck Marvin, Charles Swisher), postcards, and journals of notes taken while a student at University of Illinois. They range in date from 1918-73, and their provenance is unclear, being accessioned to the University Archives in 1995.
  - Photos of home, garden, and cat; postcards (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Photo of Nazi officer, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photos, people and buildings (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Photos, article on Pres. Lincoln's log cabin (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Family photos (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Lion's Club Certificate of Appreciation, 02/12/1963 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Col. Richard Stockton, VI, photo, 11/24/1943 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Photos of home, garden, and cat (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Photos of home and garden (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Portrait (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Curtis Wilgus, portrait, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Armband with "Deutche Wehrmacht", miscellaneous photos, article on Pres. Lincoln's log cabin (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous photos, postcards, photo collage (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Tom Hutchison, 10/15/1942 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Magazine page of a man's portrait (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Portrait of US Army Colonel, Signal Corps (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Portrait of a Man (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Photos of cat, friends; postcards (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Portrait of William Collier, former Pres. GWU, 1918 ca. (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Group portrait (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Group portrait (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - MCL and AA Champions, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Photos, photos of house, garden, family and cat, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Postcards; portraits of a woman (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Portraits, family photos (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Portraits, family photos (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Univ. Of Illinois, Highest Scholarship, photo, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Catedrale de Bourges, Vitrail de l'Apocalypse, 13th century, overhead copy (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Portrait of a woman, miscellaneous photos (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Charles Clinton Swisher, History professor, 06/02/1926 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous photos and portraits (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous photos; postcards; group Army officer photo (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Army Commendation Ribbon Citation, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Magazine page of painting by Grant Wood (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Photos of young friends, group portrait (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Three men talking (professors?) (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Army group portrait, photos of friends and family (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Council of Civil War, 06/02/1864 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Hall of Government, GWU (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - President Marvin, portrait (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Fort Union, print color copy (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - L'hotel de Ville, Le Point Rouge, color print (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "Illinois Militia, Black Hawk War" color print and accompanying description of uniforms; 2 small female portraits (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "Arbor Day" copy of painting by Grant Wood (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Portrait, unknown man (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "11th Indiana Volunteers" color print of uniforms (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - "Lvtetia, Vulgo Paris 1600, Pickett's Charge," color print (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Poster of a glacier, gift from eldest daughter, Lee (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - "Merton College" color print (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Name plaque, "Wood Gray" (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Notebook of notes Wood Gray took while a student at University of Illinois [1/3], 1926-1931 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Notebook of notes Wood Gray took while a student at University of Illinois [2/3], 1926-1931 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Notebook of notes Wood Gray took while a student at University of Illinois [3/3], 1926-1931 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Volume 1 of an index to an unidentified newspaper for the year 1808, 1808 ca. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Volume 2 of an index to an unidentified newspaper for the year 1808, 1808 ca. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Framed George Washington Coat of arms transparency (Box 7, Folder 6)